Welcome again
Section 2, chapter 2, whatever you want to say
In this we are going to talk about the network topologies
Now we know what is computer when we can't computer to each other. This is a network now
Something you have to study by all and what you have to study by all. I will tell you it is
course, so yeah
Keep your eyes and mind open
So why I am starting with a mesh topology
So there's a very step of topologies. We have in our network. There's a purse. This is star
These are the we can say a basic bus topology. This is a basic
Connecting 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 system in a serial
There's a bus topology, but why I'm going to start with a mesh topology
You will get this answer just be with me
so in mesh topology
everybody device has dedicated point of point linking to to every other device
This creates a highly interconnected network where each node communicates directly with every other node
It's often considered the most robust and reliable network to project you to its extensive redundancy
Now here what happened is that there's a different systems which connected to each other like one is connected to two
Two is connected to three and three is connected to one and that's how like
Everything is connected just like a web web over for
Spider okay, so everything is connected to each other
So even if one system fail
There's a no
Chances of failover, okay, but it is expensive because you have to put a different links to each other and you have to add
things to each
Connection to each other so for that you have to be using a different networking devices
This will cost build with cost height, but redundancy is so much
The high number of connections means that you finally feels data can simply be read out to throw another path
That's what I'm saying a fun path for system get fed data will can simply be routed
Throw another path. There's a various path and this makes mesh topology
Adder for critical network, so if you network it's highly highly critical
Okay, mesh topology is the best one if budget is not your concern
Wear uptime and data and equity are paramount such as in data center or high decoding movements
Now mesh topology can be further characterized full mesh of partial mesh full mesh is the one that is everything is connected to each other
But it's
What does it does advantage is extreme cost and maintain a challenge and what is a partial mesh?
Only some notes are directly corrected a note might need to traverse another note to reach a destination
Offering a balance between a redundancy and cost
Next
I
Met topology. I don't know someone is cooking his food and
There's a lot of mice coming from us around me
Okay, let's back to a bird of it
Master clergy strength and weakness
Now you know whatever strength it will never go down highly efficient. You will be robust. There is a redundancy one fault tolerance
It is for what is fault tolerance for dash like if something was went like something goes down something
Was unplanned. We still have a redundancy is there same still get data
Okay, they we still have a route we still have a route to get that data
So mesh topology offer a parallel reality reliability and data liquidity
Make it at your for environments with network uptime and data security at paramount
How would this commit to convert cold cold posting terms of infrastructure complexity?
Advantage just remember
Move what is mesh topology so mesh topages connected to each other. So according to deck according to that you have get you
Advantage and disadvantage you don't need to learn these things. Okay, just visualize this what is advantage highly efficient
extremely robust
Right in hand security, where is it is because where we have a network uptime and data security at paramount?
So like in a we have a different application of training
Training when we do a stroke training they use this app of mesh topology because they even they get a
two-second of loss
It goes their company reputation and in a billion billion out orders. Okay, so that's why it's
Should be it should be a mesh topology
Now you know why I started from a mesh topology. This is the reason it's highly recommend if your if your concern is not a budget
No, it's a fault identification and data is highly reliable. We know on risk of loss or corruption over dedicated links
No, they say advantages. It will take up cost. Okay, installation
Configuration are time complex consuming and complex due to number of connection
Highly maintenance cost definitely, but if you have you if you are owner of company and you
Can't equal to manage like you don't want or even a single time down time
It's single second of downtime goes to millions of millions of millions of millions of millions then definitely we're ready to pay
Okay
Record extensive cabling leading to high material cost making it best for limited number to us
Typically every must have a person number of ports. Yes, just so they come up with our own words
Yeah, definitely so you have to be
Extended with no ports as well, you know device to connect to each other
So this is all thing that tip you have to be designed in mind and after that
Every time you say clearly that this is the advantage and this will be that this advantage of this topology
The same thing I return over here for you. It's just in a more better way
So you can write down in your notebook if you want to
If you're so if at the last moment of when you are preparing for an interview
You don't have to be
Like from where I have to learn or you have to do over these are the best just
Pin out the bold one and explain it to into where
Okay
I just asked for mass topology and personal methodology said these are the definitions, which I did you find free
So the same difference sir, if you want to say a bike
There's a different way to define your bike. Okay, so some the same way
I can define the same word in different definitions
The one you showed you you can go with okay, and these were the best one which I highlighted
So you go with it
Now what is a ring topology and a standing of ring topology
Device are connected in a circular closed part data path each network device is connected to easily to other
Forming a contraines circle data tables from one device to next until it's reached its destination
This topology can be used in both land and when
Okay, so land stand for local area work and find itself wider
So local area network is so limited like there is a location
You have university it is a land you have quality you have land you have a company small
You have a company one-in-sense fresco you one in Germany one in India and in India
You have multiple locations of your company
One in Google one is both are the one is on telling so every
Single is the every single one is a land and when it's connected to each other it is a one
Okay
Ring topology a cat address by data for direction now. How here the main part is a key feature of ring topology at
It's use of token which carries data over around the ring only the device without token can touch the data
Preventing all collision ensure all the combination. Yeah, so when there's a any
communication is going on like
To in a message. You want any network. How it going to be happen?
I'm sending data my friend is sending data that it will get colloid
Okay, the data get colloid and that there is a real real loss of it up
So it will effect so he's sending me love you and I get only you so how can I say that my data is correct or
This is truly any appropriate way. So here we have a token
So when what token is with my friend? He will send me text when token is with me
I will send him a text one once the token is with someone else he can send us
But we can't send us so this is how it prevent collision and it makes sure that only
Convocation is going on now here in ring topology
It will be a unit extra of eye direction. What is your direction like?
There is a very circular more clockwise direction or
Anti-clockwise direction but in bidirection they can be both
Like I can send and receive at the same clock or anti-clockwise
Okay, that that's a difference
You can see they'll return over a data can move in at that direction offering some redundancy in case a single three areas
So if one link get very still have a come communication between them
Now ring topologies of re-implement an in-environmental particular data
Taspeter and collision avoidance are critical through its abundance on each note one out of a credit to get a ticket. It's in over 12
Totally whatever you advantage on whatever you're doing. There's another now before we move ahead
We're ring technology is merely used
So I have a manufacturing company. I have I take company
I have a strike strike strike company
Now my one server room is there
Okay, if you want me to I can't explain in more better way
For that just give me one note
Hi, so now what we know
We talked about
Mesh topology, we talked about ring topology
Let's start with the first apology
How it is
was
To go
But device connected to another twice another twice another twice
Another
Twice now this is a bus topology a data we've transferred from this
This reduction is here here here here here
Here, okay, it can be depend on the which turn which system turn right now depend on that now
To remove this I have to use
It is a nothing
No, this is motorizer. Where is the eraser?
I don't know where it is. I just going to copy this
Delete
Okay, I don't know. So I just for you guys. I just install this application takes planet in a more better way
No
We talked about ring topology
This system
And I am here talking, I'm making a drawing of
System systems which is computer
But it will be a switch
Okay, a switch of a port a switch of
Show this port a six-day port
It depends on you. Okay, so it will get switched which is connected in this way and with this switch
A PC is connected. Okay, at that particular location
So what actually I was trying to say why we use ring topology
is that
How to make this smaller
Yeah
I don't know where it is
Delete, okay, there is a delete option
Oh
So I have to just explain you
You know first way
No, you have a server room here
server room
Hub room
No, I'm writing hub room
There is a core
Core new to no core. It's completely okay. There is a switch
Okay, there is a switch there is a switch
Switch is connected to each other
Okay, now
This have
20 user stiff size 50 user
This area have five user
And this is a server room
So it will provides connection to all or it can be a rack
rack full of switches
Okay, so we I will talk about this as well
That what is a rack? What is a switch? Definitely we will talk about this
Now
When there is any fluctuation is going on any
Something like there is a fault there is a fault in a cable, which is going here where this is a row
So yeah, so there is something fault is going on here
And it will disconnect this now this location
How it going to be uh internet how it going to be
Get that internet that server access will be everything
How is this will be the direction
Okay, it will this will be the direction
This will this will be direction and this will be direction
So why it is a better than mesh because you don't have to be of this spend you a lot of money
You have a good internet network. You have fault turbulence is there
So this is what we I'm going to say that
uh
This is now
Okay, ignore if any failure here every now's ignore there now. What is a messed up logic?
Switch
Connected
Okay, everything is team team team team team team
You get three three
Now
Now what?
It is expensive
But yeah, make sure
This one get disconnected you still have a network
This water is there you still have a network
How this process?
Okay
Anyway, I can actually use still have this way
You still have this way. So this is the mother
If one getting extra you still have two parts. So it is very used in a very uh
Some big big companies big big companies which can't
Able to total it any fault when Amazon uh in trading companies in uh Google they use it
Okay, let's move ahead
Yeah, I have to pause this
Yeah, so as we see go through the
our
Task port
Let's
Get it where we live. Okay, so what will the advantage and what will be the disadvantage single point of failure
The failure the one would condition the entire network. This is not a possible condition
So it is you have to decide what is true and what is not true. So it is not it is false
The current troubleshooting I don't think the example of affiliate can be challenging. No
No
Data back kid delay data must pass through intermediate notes before reaching its engineering grid latency
True let's say curve data pass through all nodes true
Disrupture changes adding or removing the station can temporarily destroy the whole network
Not whole, but yeah, it will it will destroy the traffic
So you use your bin here that what is what is to what is not true? I'm just
Add it in drawbacks to make you aware to make you up
Okay, so yeah, I'd want to minimal packet collision
Definitely we use token here high speed
Definitely because we have for location is too easy
A transmission we do first because we using a
Single line single way cancel connections cable
We can use double as well, but yeah, the speed will be higher robust and scalable highly highly scalable
Most of the companies more to start the companies use training highly scalable. Okay low data loss definitely as we
In our first point we use we say minimal packet loss
minimal minimal packet collision so the same in here load to us
Okay, here will be the the same thing
You can say and it will be a different definitions
You can so I'm just pause it and write it down if you want to read it if you want to
What is a tree topology, so the hierarchical structure the topology, right?
The structure where diverse are connecting a way to a similar tree with a root load at the top
Leave at the bottom and where is the branches in between the root node is going to do multiple charlotte's forming a clear hierarchy
This type of topology is essentially a variation of stark place away to multiple stark and network are connected to whether
In today was a result of one central load
Acting the trunk and each subsequent load is connected to a physical path note can be
Thought of as a branch is coming off the trend file. Hello. I'm put a efficient organization and expansion
Data pleasure probably effective for creative large and with a complex network providing a structure of plus two and all of those
Modelly the tree topology, but what I'm going to run is now you know what is a tree
It is over there is a one stem at the top then there is a
Two at the bottom now every node have two at the bottom
So this is how a tree will be going to be designed
I will tell you in a dashboard. We know that whiteboard
After a few minutes after completion of this
I will tell you what will be the advantage and disadvantage is easy to add new devices. Yeah, you can easily add
One device in any other node
Redirection correlation. Very easy to do structure
I recall you definitely so we can easily able to do that when the invite at which point there is a error
Okay, a lot for a number of simulations as well as traffic and protests certain network segments
You can say that in this
Four node is going to be a different network. It is for come to video different over. This is how you can separate
Superious capabilities definitely high speed data transfer moment notes with the branch and throw the control
Definitely not over if the center trunk fails then the system can go down impacting all connect romances
Yeah, so if top level or if mid-level any
A node going to be afraid
The below that node will also going to be a disturb
They're not able to access the internet. They're not able to get the services
Installation questions. I don't know. It's difficult for co-connecting branches to protect. Yes
Deconification can be difficult when new devices were added
Especially if required major structure changes. Yes, you can run call volume of cables. I know this helps your support of branches structure
Definitely
Hypotrophysic the pest from both work. No
If I'm saying that linked topology is widely used
I'm also want to say hybrid topology is one of the most widely used
Because because there is a worried topology now
After there is a switch I said there is a
One cable connect there is a ports there's a six ports of on this
Definitely there is a eight port. So it puts is going to connect it with a single
System single system when we talk about system. It's computer. It can be a laptop single system now
This is a bus. This is a star like one. There is a
Switch and switch is connected to different
System so this is forming
We can say star now the whole network gets hybrid. It is
Connect combination of two topologies or ring and a star
It is a powerful combination of two or more different type of network. Whether it is a positive play
Deployed when the network is in need to accommodate a reversal requirement. Yeah, it's totally depend on the requirement
We have or integrated extremely towards the one the flexibility of hybrid topology allow for highly customite and optimized network solution
That can represent the various layout while mitigating their individual weakness
Come example include the star ring topology
Yeah, as I said before before reading this
Where multiple star network are connected? We are a ring back book. Yeah, or the star bus topology
Definitely which could several star network throw us and it will have
Bus, sorry hybrid topology. Our program is for a large organization with the various to dominate or
When expanding is a standard way infrastructure
Therefore, scalability of tolerance by distributing network traffic and product during the path
There will be advantage. There will be
Disadvantage advantages
Combine the advantage for both
multiple topology so
optimizing their performance and reliability is depend on the type of topology you use and
Definitely you are going to use that topology will provide more performance more reliability and more optimizing the network
Highly flexible long for customer network segment design to meet a specific organization
The size of network can be explained by the adding new device
Whatever additional son network can be designed to be full tolerant inserting continuous operational even one segment first. Yes
Probability change it to design architecture of hybrid network due to its competitive. Yes. Yes
So if you're going to make a ring topology and then there is a start-up logic
It will it will it will be your heart time
Okay
Hubs and other network in common using type of topology are often expensive
If you're making a ring topology for the security, you're going to use a firewall and there's a switch in there
And the switches connected to other hardware
So this will definitely
First way this will definitely takes a lot of networking devices
And it will cost a little bit more
Recom financing can be difficult when you do as it are added
It's basically if you look at major structures changes. Yes. Yes. Yes
Require large volume of cables and numerous hubs to support the branch extractor definitely
So this is once again, you can read
hybrid representation work
So you can see the difference
In the previous in this one. So it's
I depend on the like I keep writing keep writing keep writing that
Of how I can say that one same thing in another way
How I can say the same advantage just matters in another format?
So you have to go through and read it and
No, they don't okay make it so that no data
Always always keep notebook with you when you're watching my lectures
understanding startup regime
so
Me startup regime all devices are usually connected to a center lab. So let us assume that there is a one
Spider and it's better is
Signing it's web all over the area
So that's how it is
There is a one up one networking device one
Switches at the center and all system are connected with each other
I can imagine a lot of horror movies related to it
I don't know why this and it was a terrible server relying on data transmission
But when the connectin would think of it like as both as a number cycle field all connected to a central
Excel. Yeah, perfect example
The setup is a value used to do it simplicity in design and management especially in small medium-side local
In network the central point control all traffic flow make it easy to manage and to go back now
Take of five minutes
Pause the screen take the five minutes and at least
Like write down the advantage and disadvantage. What it can be
For robust if bowling fails only that is specific connection is affected not than Dan network easy fault identification and aspiration definitely
Okay, cost effective cabling. Yes, look at rapid data transfer
Yes, single point of failure next central and the switch get filled entire network become
Inoperable in operational
highly cost if in install is cost is because there is a great cable
And there will be
Center hub and the configuration of that performing dependency
Your network performance in telephone on the capacity and efficiency of central controller high cable requirement each device need to
Dedicate cable to central hub in case cable management complexity in large interval. Yes
cable requirement is there
Performance dependency on a central is there installation configuration take and time cost and time both will affect and there's a single part of failure
Now, what is a extended start topology?
It is also known as hierarchical topology built upon the basic star network by connecting multiple start network thrower additional
Networking device to place which is instead of all device connected to a central single hub. They correct the local intermediate versus switch
which are then connected to main central devices
Another intermediate versus just greater layer
Microstructured along for a create a skillability and the punishment of allows you to report that then assembly star
And the second it was simply a middle was which is intent correct or there is interval over the forming a multi
Multital star system. This make it a total test for large
organization and campus number campus network. Now, there will be a one central hub now if this central hub a multiple
Central hub will be connected and these have have a different
Own star network. Okay, so this will connect to a different system different devices
so multiple star devices are forming
Connecting a single star network devices to make an extended start of logic
KTVF case from all of us. Yeah, so this type of topologies. We have this tour
We have talked about star master reading hybrid and extended star
Okay, the T topology we discussed. There's another definition of T topology. You can use this is how the structure will be there
Needed there will be advantage and did disadvantage. Can go through it. How this hybrid topology and extended start of which will look like the same way
It is in a diagram
You can hear
No, what will the advantage and data advantage?
So this was the common advantages and disadvantages that you have to just remember this point at this point fixed to
Like most people it wet at which topology you had to decide that
Okay
No
Again trade topology. Why I'm writing again everything here because you can remember that this type of topology. We have
Again, we there is a there's a scalability fault. I should have some high speed data network
Prioritizer central term failure I kept because
How do one is you don't have to do them? I just
Make sure that
This if there's a high capable cost where it will be used. It is used in a mass topology
extended start of low g
Topology where a high cable can use ring topology is not that case because they're a type
Cable are not used. Okay, in hybrid if they're using a start of low g
Then definitely a trade topology high high cable cost. So yeah, you have to remember that
So these are the some points that you have to remember only and
Just read one one by everything. Okay
Food rated you will remember it when you have to tell
This will be the end of the our presentation. Let's get back to over a wider
No, so now you know
We're gonna come into this
Let's we talked about mass topology. We talked about ring topology now we talk about a startup regime
This will be our switch
Connected to one system connected to one system connected to one system connected to one system
Connected to one system. This will be our
Star
Okay, start of low g is this
No, I know how to remove this you have to double tap. So how you do just
Select
Select everything
Double tap. Okay, I said you I will learn this how to use it
Same here. Okay, now let's move it with a different
Then no, I know start what is external stuff
This will be help
Any switch connect to device connect to device connect to device connect to device
This switch is connected to a main switch
Okay, the same network is adapted here the same network as it depicted here the same network is attributed here the same network is attributed here
Okay, I don't know how to do a copy paste
But I'm just trusting this
So this is called a extender
Star topology
No
Okay, just remove this as well
Now, I know worrying. I know star. I know
Tell no, I don't know this one connect to this
This is how everything works here, okay
Cable uses trees fault
All it were going to be test out
Okay, now what else you can think of?
What else you can think of will be effect
Now I have there's a network issue here. Do you not able to access this system
More likely where you can say that there will be a report
Fall will be definitely in this cable
Okay, so it easy to
Find a fault it is easily to find a fault
No, let's move more. Let's move easy to add new devices
Okay easy to add new devices easy to add new devices
Okay
device
Easy
The enhancement of a network is there scalable of network is there
Okay, so yeah, this is what we talked about
Okay
Let's move. Oh
I think we talked about everything. We lost everything
There's a hybrid. Hyperveria talking about
Ring technology
Well, however, I would talk about heartbeat
Previously as well, but yeah, I'm gonna tell you again
The now system is connected and there is a
system are connected to the
switches
Computers laptop
A ring topology a star topology
Arous, no, here system connected system. Okay. So it's from wherever
Are the
That's how this network works. It is very easy. This you have to
Imagine like what you're going to do. What is your requirement?
It all depend on that
So
So if you're going to next after
Like
Just kidding
Just give a comment
What you like in this course
Okay
My
Frank is not that good, but okay, you just try to what is model like what you don't like so I can increase
Or decrease depend on that
Whatever you comment and thank you for
for chasing this course. Thank you for paying this course
Just to be honest to be honest
Okay, as a man. I'm saying this this is
Definitely then I'm going to do seeing it from my hurts. Okay from the bottom of my hurts
I really love you guys
And just have me from where I used
This as an example to teach you which network
Okay, just comment down below. Thank you. Thank you so much